Stanislaw E. Bask-Mostwin Collection CPAA 94.01
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Stanislaw E. Bask-Mostwin collection
1975-1992
CPAA 94.01
Connecticut Polish American Archives
2.0 Linear feet
Stanislaw Edward Bask Mostwin was an achieved war hero and political activist in his lifetime. He was awarded several military decorations during WWII and after immigrating to the United States became actively involved in Polish and Polish American causes. He belonged to groups such as the Polish National Democratic Committee, Polish Heritage Society in Maryland, Polish American Congress, and North American Study Center for Polish Affairs (STUDIUM). The collection includes papers from these groups, especially STUDIUM, and other essays and writings on the state of Poland at the time and its history.
Mostwin, Stanislaw Edward Bask
Biographical/Historical note
Stanislaw Edward Bask Mostwin was a lawyer, engineer, Polish Army officer, and a political activist in various Polish American organizations. Mr. Mostwin was born in Poznan, Poland in 1917, where he attended the Poznan University School of Law. In 1945 he graduated with a law degree from Warsaw Underground University School of Law. He attended The Officers Cavalry School in Grudziadz. After WWII he attended engineering training in England and George Washington University School of Law in Washington DC.
Stanislaw Mostwin took active part in military operations in September of 1939. He was wounded and awarded Virtuti Militari, the highest military decoration for heroism and courage. He escaped from Poland in 1940 via Palestine and enlisted with the Polish Carpathian Brigade under British command. He participated in the North African campaign where he was wounded and awarded the Virtuti Militari for the second time. In 1943 he was sent to England where he participated in training for the Special Forces and completed training for the British Intelligence. In 1944 he became a special emissary of the Polish government-in-exile and traveled to Poland. He parachuted behind Polish lines in May of 1944. He participated in the Warsaw Uprising and cooperated with the Polish Underground. In 1945 he married Danuta Pietruszewska (who became an author and sociologist) in Warsaw. In December of the same year, facing arrest by the secret police, he escaped with his family to England.
In England, under auspices of the Polish Resettlement Corps, he completed engineering training and in 1951 immigrated to the U.S. with his wife and son. He settled in Baltimore where he worked at several textile companies as an engineer and designer. He also attended George Washington University Law School.
Mr. Mostwin and his wife Danuta were very active in working on behalf of their homeland. Mr. Mostwin was an active member of the Polish National Democratic Committee in Washington, a co-founder of the Polish Heritage Society of Maryland, and national director of the Polish American Congress. In 1975 he was a co-founder and later vice-president of the North American Study Center for Polish Affairs (STUDIUM), an academic think tank that examined Polish political affairs from the U.S. perspective.
He was a strong advocate for the Polish-Jewish dialogue. He was a chairman of the STUDIUM Committee on Polish-Jewish dialogue and established the Janusz Korczak Literary Award for children's literature. Janusz Korczak was an assimilated Polish Jew, working as a children's writer, educator, and pediatrician. His real name was Henryk Goldszmit. Before the war he established an orphanage for Jewish children. During WWII the orphanage was moved inside the Warsaw Ghetto and in August of 1942 all were sent to Treblinka and put to death. Korczak received many offers to be smuggled outside the ghetto but he did not want to abandon his children.
In the 1990's Mostwin worked on further dialogues with other ethnic groups and organized a conference between Polish Americans and German Americans in Washington, DC. In 1980's he was involved in gathering congressional and financial support for Solidarity in Poland and after Martial Law was established he was involved in getting support for the Solidarity support groups organized in the US. Mr. Mostwin wrote many analytical essays on Poland's independence and Polish-Jewish relations. In recent years his activism diminished. He died on May 30, 2011 at the age of 94.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of material related to the establishment and activities of STUDIUM from 1975 until the mid 1990's, documented by correspondence, minutes, membership, treasurer reports, publications and position papers. It includes articles and historical essays on the history of Poland, economy, and current political situation in Poland the Eastern bloc. It also includes records of the Polish American Congress and records of other organizations of which Mr. Mostwin was a member.
Separated Materials note
Serial publications were removed and added to our circulating serial collection.
North American Study Center for Polish Affairs; NSZZ "Solidarność" (Labor organization); Poland -- History -- 20th century; Poland -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Polish American Congress; Polish Americans Societies, etc.; Polish people -- United States
- Stanislaw Bask-Mostwin - CV and obituary, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Stanislaw Bask-Mostwin – articles, writings, notes, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Studium – statut i deklaracja ideowa [Constitution and by-laws], June 14, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Studium – correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Studium - clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Studium – situation in Poland – articles, clippings, from Polish-American and American press, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Studium - correspondence, resolutions, memos, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence with F. Wilk from England, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Studium – II-gi Walny Zjazd [Second Convention], June 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Studium - correspondence, resolutions, memos, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Studium - correspondence, resolutions, memos, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Studium – list of members, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Studium – correspondence with Anna Poray-Wybranowski, Canada, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Studium – protokoly z posiedzen [minutes of meetings], scattered issues, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Studium – oswiadczenia programowe [mission statement], 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Studium – publications of interest to Studium, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Studium – protocols, minutes and material related to various activities within organization, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Studium – financial records, tax exemption, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- List otwarty do zespolu redakcyjnego pisma Bratniak, by Jacek Kuron [Open letter to publishers of magazine Bratniak], 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Piotr Harcaj – correspondence and writings, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Piotr Harcaj – obituary, in memoriam, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Studium – correspondence, press releases, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Studium – financial statement, December 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Studium – survey on organizational changes and program, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Studium – plan strategiczny na lata 1990-93 zalozenia i kierunki dzialania: material do dyskusji [Strategic plan], 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Studium – Ewa Gierat treasurer, correspondence and related material, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Europejskie Studium Spraw Polskich – project statutu [Studium European division - by-laws project] (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letters from Waclaw Soroka related to Studium, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- “Walka o dusze narodu – walka o prawde i moralne odrodzenie [Struggle for nation's soul - struggle for truth and moral revival]”, by Waclaw W. Soroka, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Uwagi Stefana Korbonskiego nad statutem Fundacji Armii Krajowej [Stefan Korbonski's notes on The Home Army Foundation], 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Correspondence with Jan Nowak (Jezioranski), 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- International Labour Office, Geneva, Switzerland – reports on Poland, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Solidarity International – correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Solidarity Coordinating Office Abroad, Brussels - statements, declarations, appeals, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Support of Solidarity groups - contact information, press releases, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Walendowski, Tadeusz – CV, underground activities, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Official Polish press on opposition, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Uchwala programowa Krajowego Zjazdu Delegatow NSZZ Solidarnosc, [Program resolution of NSZZ Solidarnosc at National Delegates Congress], Gdansk, April, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Program NSZZ Solidarnosc uchwalony przez I Krajowy Zjazd Delegatow [Trade Union Solidarity Programme adopted by the First National Congress of Delegates], in Tygodnik Solidarnosc no.29, Oct. 16, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Father Jerzy Popieluszko – his kidnapping and death, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Address by Senator Styles Bridges (R - N.H.) at the Freedom Rally, New York, April 11, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Situation in Poland – clippings from Polish press, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Correspondence and writing by Kazimierz Plater-Zyberek on situation in Poland, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Jan F. Morelewski – CV and nomination for Polish Army Major, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Komendant “Wilk” Krzyzanowski, article by Jan F. Morelewski, from Orzel Bialy, February 1982 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Polish Heritage Association of Maryland, Inc. – By-laws [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Maryland Action for Poland, Inc. – By laws and Articles of Incorporation, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Maryland Action for Poland Committee - correspondence and related material, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Slavic- Americans in Maryland - current ethnic issues, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Kongres Polonii Kanadyjskiej [Polish Canadian Congress] - correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- “The yesterday and the today of the Polish community in Canada”, by Tadeusz Brzezinski [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 51)
- PAC National - memos, speeches, correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- PAC National - Board meetings, reports, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Position of PAC on cultural exchange between US and Poland, by Andrzej Ehrenkreutz, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 54)
- “Background and realities of the Polish “free and unfettered elections” of Jan. 19, 1947, by Blandyna Ehrenkreutz (Box 1, Folder 55)
- “Yalta and Poland” by Blandyna Ehrenkreutz [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Yalta agreement controversy, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Teaching Holocaust, 1975-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Polish-Jewish relations, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Auschwitz convent controversy – correspondence, clippings, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Polish Jewish relations, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- “Jews, Poles and anti-Semitism” by W.W., in Polityka Polska, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Auschwitz convent controversy – correspondence, clippings, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Polish-Jewish relations testimonials, 1946; 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Polish-Jewish relations clippings, 1975-1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Studium – Janusz Korczak Literary Competition and related correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Korczak Literary Competition Awards – financial records, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Karren, Tamara, "Who was this man?": monodrama; translated by Jacek Laskowski [London]: [s.n.], a play portraing Janusz Korczak, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence re: Dialogus Press Fund, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Dialogus Press Fund – financial records, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Richard T. Davis, US Ambassador to Poland, biography, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Amnesty International, Poland - press releases, flyers, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Human rights issues – various publications, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- “Vive La Pologne” revisited by Josef Lubanski, January 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- “Man and Knowledge: One or two systems”; “What is Solidarity?” by Jerzy A. Wojciechowski from University of Ottawa, 1980; 1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- “The Polish American Experience” an essay by Thaddeus C. Radzilowski, 1980's (Box 2, Folder 26)
- “Executive report of feasibility study” by Karol M. Borowski from The Center for Suburban and Regional Studies of Towson State University, October 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Statistics of the Nationalities of the USSR; The Problem of totalitarianism: A view from The United States; The nationality question in the Soviet Union; The Conspiracy: Planning for economic collapse, issued by the Council of the European Liaison Group (photocopies), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Konfederacja Polski Niepodleglej – deklaracja ideowa [Confederation of Independent Poland - program], 1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Przeglad prasy ukrainskiej w opracowaniu J. Lobodowskiego z Ministerstwa Spraw Zagranicznych, London, Feb. 1983 [Ukrainian Press review by J. Lobodowski, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Polish Government in Exile, London, February 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- “O niektorych postawach w opozycji” by Waldemar Kuczynski [The attitudes of some figures in the opposition movement], [after 1983] (Box 2, Folder 31)
- “Visions and reality” article from POLITYKA, no.48 by Stanislaw Kwiatkowski, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Cooperation in the field of economics of science and technology and of the environment, chapter on Poland, [after 1986] (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Correspondence with Jan Plater-Gajewski re: Poles in Kazachstan, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Projekt Konstytucji Rzeczpospolitej Polskiej, by Jozef Litynski [The draft Constitution of the Polish Republic], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Poland’s renewal and U.S. options. A Policy reconnaissance, by John P. Hardt, CRS, June 1987-update, 1989 – draft (photocopies), 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- “Comments on a very painful matter” by Jozef Garlinski, copy of an article from Tydzien Polski, London, Oct. 18, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Stan zdrowia ludnosci I zagrozenie ekologiczne w Polsce, by Jerzy Grebski and Maria Nowak, Zurich [The health status of the population and the ecological threat in Poland], September, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Miscellaneous - articles, clippings, press releases from various organizations, 1980's (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Zjazd Polonii Wolnego Swiata [Congress of the Free World Polonia] - program, official pamphlets, resolutions, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Starczewski, Walenty – correspondence with senators re: events in Poland, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- A proposal for a Polish agreement on independence, prepared by A.K.D., an essay related to Poland's Consitution, [1980's] (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Zalozenia wstepne fundacji “Promocja ekonomiczna Polakow w ZSRR” by Jan Wieslaw Krasnodebski, [Presuppositions of the Foundation, "Economic promotion of Poles in the USSR] (Box 2, Folder 43)
- “Nie zaplodnione jajo” by Tadeusz Boguszewski, an essay about political situation in Poland after the Martial Law, [1982]; Mostwin, Stanislaw Edward Bask (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Remarks of President Reagan at luncheon for Polish American leaders, Aug. 17, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- “Wklad gospodarczy pokolenia Polski niepodleglej 19181-1939 [Economic contribution of generation of the Independent Poland 1918-1939” by Lukasz Czuma, Sep. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- German revisionism on German-Polish border - correspondence, essays, clippings, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- "Uprising and organic work in the XIXth century", by Stefan Kieniewicz (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Poland and the United States since World War II: A Historical Survey, by Piotr S. Wandycz, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Oredzie Edwarda Raczynskiego, Prezydenta Rzeczypospolitej na 11 listopada, 1983, London [Statement of Edward Raczynski, President of the Polish Government in Exile for November 11, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Polish Government in Exile – publications, 1980’s, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Znad Wilii - dwutygodnik polski, Wilno, Rok I, no. 2-3 [Polish language newspaper], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Various photographs of Wladyslaw Sikorski from Krajowa Agencja Wydawnicza (Box 2, Folder 53)
- The Warsaw Uprising - original photographs with captions in Polish, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Round Table discussion in Poland – US response, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Stanislaw Bask-Mostwin – material separated (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Copy of the Proclamation signed by President George H. Bush to honor the 200th anniversary of the Polish Constitution, May 1991 (Box 2, Oversize 1)
- Audio tape - Wielki glod na Ukrainie 1932/33 [Great Ukrainian famine 1932/33], interview with Prof. Roman Szporluk by Jerzy Rozalski, WPON Detroit rubber stamp with logo – Maryland Action for Poland (Box 2, Object 1)